Some memories are best forgotten.
Memento is a mystery, thriller film directed by Christopher Nolan.
Leonard Shelby is tracking down the man who raped and murdered his wife.
The difficulty of locating his wife's killer, however, is compounded by the fact that
he suffers from a rare, untreatable form of short-term memory loss.
Although he can recall details of life before his accident, Leonard cannot
remember what happened fifteen minutes ago, where he's going, or why.
Leonard, played by Guy Pearce.
Natalie, played by Carrie-Anne Moss.
Teddy, played by Joe Pantoliano.
Burt, played by Mark Boone Junior.
Waiter, played by Russ Fega.
Leonard's Wife, played by Jorja Fox.
Memento is a 2000 American psychological thriller film written and directed by Christopher Nolan, based on the
short story "Memento Mori" by his brother Jonathan Nolan, which was later published in 2001.
The film stars Guy Pearce, Carrie-Anne Moss, and Joe Pantoliano.
It follows Leonard Shelby (Pearce), a man who suffers from anterograde amnesia—resulting in short-term memory loss and the inability to form new memories—who uses an
elaborate system of photographs, handwritten notes, and tattoos in an attempt to uncover the perpetrator who killed his wife and caused him to sustain the condition.
The film's non-linear narrative is presented as two different sequences of scenes interspersed during the film: a series in black-and-white that is shown
chronologically, and a series of color sequences shown in reverse order (simulating for the audience the mental state of the protagonist).
The two sequences meet at the end of the film,
producing one complete and cohesive narrative.
Memento premiered at the Venice Film Festival on September 5, 2000, and was
theatrically released in the United States on March 16, 2001.
It was acclaimed by critics, who praised its nonlinear structure and
themes of memory, perception, grief, and self-deception.
It was also a commercial success, earning $40 million over its
$9 million budget and gained a cult following.
Memento received many accolades, including the Waldo Salt Screenwriting Award at the Sundance Film
Festival, and Academy Award nominations for Best Original Screenplay and Best Film Editing.
In 2017, the United States Library of Congress deemed the film "culturally, historically, or
aesthetically significant" and selected it for preservation in the National Film Registry.
The film explores themes of drug dealer, amnesia, insulin, tattoo, waitress.
The tone is intense and dark and mind_bending.